TTerm – Introduction

Back to index.

What do you need TTerm for?

Android runs on top of a (small) Linux layer. To call Linux commands interactively, you need a "shell" that runs in a "terminal emulator". The shell calls the Linux commands, the terminal emulator displays your input and the commands' output.

Android comes with a shell, but not with a terminal emulator, that's what you need TTerm for.

I'll try to explain everything that I found difficult when I started using Linux on Android. But you need familiarity with Linux or Unix to understand this. If you don't understand anything that's written here, have a look at a book about Linux for beginners before you continue. Yes, a book about Linux, not a book about Android.

Android's shell

Android's shell is in /system/bin/sh. Since Android 4.0 it is the MirBSD Korn shell, also called Mksh, see Android's shell.

If you are used to a different shell or distribuition, you can install it and have TTerm start it, see Shells and distributions.

For the impatient

For the impatient that start using TTerm right away: If TTerm does not behave as you expect, look at the following settings:

UTF-8
Input method: character based or word-based
Alt key sends ESC
Terminal type
Send mouse events

I'll add more details in the future.

Starting a different shell

You can change the shell that is started with the setting Command line. See Shells and distributions for examples.

You can specify an Initial command that is sent to the shel as user input, i.e. as if you had typed it.

Running a command from the home screen

You can use the TTerm widget to run a command from an icon on the home screen.

TTerm – Changelog

Back to index.

Features

Version 0.1.9 (beta) on 2017-..-..

The setting Default to UTF-8 is now checked by default. This is necessary to get non-ASCII characters like "á ä æ ı š б א".
Fixed Bug 005, Alt-Gr does not work on hardware keyboards.

Apparently a configuration issue, documented how to fix it.

Version 0.1.8 (beta) on 2017-11-21

Bug fix: "Ctrl" didn't always fit in the button. Thanks to Norbert Copones for the bug report.
Text in extra buttons is no longer in all caps on Samsung devices.

Version 0.1.7 (beta) on 2017-08-05

Bug fix: TTerm crashed if you pressed buttons before the app was fully initialized. Thanks to JaRR92 for the bug report.

Version 0.1.6 (beta) on 2017-07-27

Bug fix for Google's keyboard GBoard for "locked Ctrl" and "locked Fn".

Tested on on-screen keyboards Google's GBoard, Hacker's Keyboard, Multiling O Keyboard and Samsung's keyboard. Also tested with a Bluetooth keyboard and a Bluetooth mini-keyboard. If it misbehaves on your keyboard, send a bug report to thorbj.hansen@gmail.com.

Bug fix for Google's keyboard GBoard for a feature of version 0.1.3: The setting Close window on exit is now off by default. When the command in the window exits, simply press Enter to close the window.
Bug fix: Action bar is now also black for Android 5+.
Improved documentation.

Version 0.1.5 (beta) on 2017-07-26

Bug fix: Use "Theme Material" for Android 5+ devices (instead of "Theme DeviceDefault").

Version 0.1.4 (beta) on 2017-07-26

The button `Ctrl´ now works in Google's keyboard "GBoard" (when typing, not when swiping).
Added a button for `Fn´.
The buttons `Ctrl´ and `Fn´ are "sticky" after one press, "locked" after two presses, see Usage: Keyboard.
Changed some of the mappings for `Ctrl´ and `Fn´, see Usage: Keyboard.
Fixed bug in shortcut "TTerm shortcut". It should always show the new window now.
"Preferences" are now called "Settings", have a gear icon and a menu entry before "Help".
Removed 4×8 pixel font. It was too small to be useful and only supported ASCII.

Version 0.1.3 (beta) on 2017-07-18

TTerm now requires at least Android 4.4 to run. If you have an older version of Android, use TEA.
Added keys for `/´ and `-´.
The setting Close window on exit is now off by default. When the command in the window exits, simply press Enter to close the window.
New service icon to distinguish TTerm from TEA, Termux and GNURoot Debian.
Improved documentation.

Version 0.1.2 (beta) on 2015-01-19

Improved documentation.
Published sources.

Version 0.1.1 (beta) on 2014-12-21

Extra keys for `Ctrl´, `Tab´, `Esc´ and the cursor keys so that you can continue using your favorite on-screen keyboard. The cursor keys have auto-repeat.

Key combinations with `Ctrl´ and `Esc´ currently only work when the setting Input mode is set to character-based.

Suggestions for swiped words do not overwrite consecutive text.

Some swipe keyboards display a suggestion which you have to commit, e.g. by pressing space or a punctuation key, or discard, e.g. by pressing backspace. For an example, try out the Google keyboard.

When typing in the middle of a line, TEA's suggestion overwrites the following text until you commit. TTerm tries to move the following text to the right. (That's not always the right thing to do, but in most cases it is more intuitive than TEA's approach.)

Example: Select the Google keyboard. Enter one two. Put the cursor on t. Enter hello without pressing space. Now TEA shows one hello, and TTerm shows one hellotwo. When you press space, TEA inserts hello and shows two again. So no text is lost, but I find TEA's behavior very confusing.

Local help files that you can read when you are offline.

At the moment, TTerm's GUI is in English, and I have no plans to translate the GUI to other languages.

To clarify: Programs running inside TTerm can run in any language, but TTerm's menu and settings are in English.

If you want your GUI in another language, you can use TEA, or you can download TTerm's sources to translate and build it yourself.

Code changes

Version 0.1.9 (beta) on 2017-..-..

Updated Android Studio 2.3.3 to 3.0.1, "Android Gradle Plugin" 2.3.3 to 3.0.1, and Gradle 3.3 to 4.1.
Merged all 3 modules into one module. The two samples `pathbroadcasts´ and `telnet´ do no longer compile.
Updated `android:targetSdkVersion´ to 25 (Android 7.1).

Version 0.1.8 (beta) on 2017-11-21

Published sources on GitHub at https://github.com/thorhans/tterm.

Version 0.1.4 (beta)

Introduced the flavor `dev´ that builds faster.
Removed lots of code and resources for Android versions older than 4.4.
Extracted class TermInputConnection from EmulatorView.onCreateInputConnection.

Version 0.1.3 (beta)

Updated to the current TEA, version 1.0.70. For details see the sources, file /docs/tea/build-tea.txt.
Increased android:minSdkVersion to 19 (Android 4.4).
TTerm now responds to TEA's intents and broadcasts.
Converted TTerm's code to compile in Android Studio.

Version 0.1.1 (beta)

Renamed package jackpal.androidterm to de.t2h.tterm so that both TEA and TTerm can be installed on a device. (That makes it harder to compare TEA and TTerm sources. Is there a better way?)
Increased android:minSdkVersion from 3 to 11.
All code changes are marked with `T+ for additions´, `T-´ for deletions and `T!´ for modifications.

TTerm – Commands

Back to index.

Commands

This list is a short documentation of the commands used in the help pages of TTerm. It's not a full list of Linux commands, and it does not cover all uses of the commands, only those that are used in the help pages of Termux.

Commands marked with "Unix", "Linux" or "shell built-in" also exist in Unix and Linux, so you can be look them up in any book or web site on Unix, BSD or Linux.

Commands marked with "Android" only exist on Android. You can google them, but there does not seem to be much information on them.

A

apt — advanced package tool

(A Linux command available in Termux and GNURoot Debian.)

See Wikipedia.

cd — change directory

(A shell built-in in all shells.)

Note that cd without arguments and cd ~ both change to the directory $HOME.

chmod — change

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

Unix uses the term "file mode" for file access rights. You change them with chmod, which in Unix supports symbolic modes and numeric modes. If you have an older Android version where /system/bin/chmod only supports numeric modes, the BusyBox version also supports symbolic modes.

A short overview:

Symbolic modes:

  chmod ([ugoa]*[+-=][rwxXst]*)+ «files»

For example:

  chmod u+rwx     # "User" may "read, write, execute".
  chomd ug+r o-r  # "User and group" may "read", "other" may not "read".
  chomd a+r       # "All" may "read".

Where

  u = user
  g = group
  o = other
  a = all

and

  + = set
  - = clear
  = = set this mode, clear the other modes

and

  r = read
  w = write
  x = for dirs:  search
      otherwise: execute
  X = for dirs:  search
      otherwise: execute if file already has execute permission for
                 some user
  s = set user or group ID on execution
  t = for dirs:  restricted deletion flag
      otherwise: sticky bit, saves file on the swap devie so it will
                 load more quickly when run

Numeric modes:

               owner  group  other
  r = read       100     10      1
  w = write      200     20      2
  x = execute    400     40      4

  t = 1000
  s             4000   2000

For example:

  chmod 777 FILE  # a+rwx

cp — copy files

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

E

echo — display a line of text

(A shell built-in in all shells, also available as a Unix command in /system/bin.)

emacs - editor

See Emacs.

env — print environment or set environment variables for a single command

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

Use 1: env

env without arguments prints the current environment.

Use 2: env «vars» «command» «arguments»

Where «vars» is «var_1»="«value 1»" ... «var_n»="«value n»". The values must be quoted or escaped as explained in Environments variables.

Executes «command» «arguments» with environment variables «var_1» to «var_n» set to the specified values.

It is equivalent to the shell syntax

«var_1»="«value 1»" ... «var_n»="«value n»" «command» «arguments»

so you only need it when you need to set environment variables but are not inside a shell. For example for the setting Command line.

exec — replace the shell with a command

(A shell built-in in all shells.)

export — set an environment variable

(A shell built-in in all sh-compatible shells.)

See section Environments variables.

F

fgrep — search for a string

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

fgrep searches files for a string.

for — execute commands for each member in a list

(A shell built-in in all sh-compatible shells.)

for «var» in «words» ; do
  «commands»
done

«words» often contains wildcards like * or a command in $(...), for example:

for i in $(echo hi ho hum) ; do
  echo "$i"
done
hi
ho
hum

G

getprop — get Android OS System Properties

(An Android command available in /system/bin.)

To access the Android OS System Properties, use:

getprop [«name» [«default»]]

Example 1: Get several properties

getprop | fgrep ro.product.m
[ro.product.manufacturer]: [samsung]
[ro.product.model]: [SM-T800]
[ro.product.name]: [chagallwifi]

Example 2: Get one property

getprop ro.product.name
chagallwifi

grep — search for a regular expression

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

grep searches files for a regular expression in.

L

ln — create a link

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

M

mkdir — make a directory

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

mkfifo — create a named pipe (a FIFO)

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

A "named pipe", also called a "FIFO" ("First In, First Out"), is a file that connects two processes with a bidirectional pipe.

For an example, see Connect to Termux with Netcat.

more — a simple pager

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

N

netcat or nc — Netcat

(A Unix command not available in /system/bin, only in BusyBox, Termux or Debian.)

Netcat can be installed as netcat, nc or both.

For an example, see Connect to Termux with Netcat.

R

rm — remove files

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

S

script — record a terminal session

(A Unix command not available in /system/bin, only in BusyBox, Termux or Debian.)

script records a terminal session, i.e. logs the input and output in a file typescript in the current directory.

set — set shell options and arguments, or print shell and environment variables

(A shell built-in in all shells.)

Use:

set without arguments prints all shell variables and environment variables. In some shells it also prints all functions.
For other uses, consult your shell's documentation. In sh-compatible shell, it sets shell options or the shell's arguments $1, $2...

setprop — set Android OS System Properties

(An Android command available in /system/bin.)

To set an Android OS System Properties, use:

setprop name value

sh — default shell

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

See Android's shell.

sort — sort lines

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

ssh — SSH

LATER I will write about this when I've found a SSH client that runs in TTerm.

su — super-user

(A Unix command only available in a rooted device.)

Use 1: su

su without arguments runs a shell as root.

Use 2: su «user»

Runs a shell as Linux user «user». In Android, each app has its own Linux user, with a name like u«android user number»_a«Linux user number».

Use 3: su [«user»] -c "«command» «args»"

Runs a command as root or Linux user «user». Note that the command and its arguments should be quoted.

stty — "set TTY", sets and prints terminal (TTY) settings

(A Unix command not available in /system/bin, only in BusyBox, Termux or Debian.)

stty has several functions:

stty size returns the terminal size. For example

$ stty size
38 84

means that the terminal has 38 rows and 84 columns.

If you only need the number of rows or the number of columns, you have to be a Shell Wizard to figure out how to access just one of the two numbers. For us ordinary mortals, BusyBox has ttysize.

It's surprisingly difficult to ensure that the currently running command always knows the current terminal size.

If something gets messed up and Linux doesn't know the current terminal size, use stty rows and stty cols to set it, for example:

stty rows 38 cols 84

stty can control terminal settings.

For example, it can enable or disable echoing of characters, and it can enable or disable the handling special characters like ^C.

The keyboard has "modes":

The default is line-based input with "cooked mode", aka "canonical mode", where the OS handles basic line editing, e.g. ^H or ^? for backspace, or ^C to interrupt.

This is a very old mode. It doesn't support cursor keys, so most shells don't use it.

For an example, start cat. You can delete a char whith Backspace, or a word with ^W, but you can't use the cursor keys.

stty raw sets the terminal to raw mode. The OS does not handle any characters, and all chars that the users types are sent immediately to the running command, and all chars output by the command are shown immediately.

This is what most shells use to offer command line editing.

For another example, see Running Termux in TTerm with Netcat, where it ensures that the remote shell handles all command line editing. It also ensures that ^C arrives at the remote shell, insted of stopping the local Netcat.

Further examples:

stty -echo turns off echoing of the chars that you type, stty echo turns it on again.

It is possible to mess up your terminal settings so that you can't even see what you are typing. In that case:

stty sane sets the terminal settings back to a "sane" default.

T

telnet, telnetd — Telnet and its daemon

(A Unix command not available in /system/bin, only in BusyBox, Termux or Debian.)

For an example, see Connect to Termux with Telnet.

ttysize — print the terminal size

(A Unix command not available in /system/bin, only in BusyBox, Termux or Debian.)

stty size returns the terminal size. But if you only need the number of rows or the number of columns, you have to be a Shell Wizard to figure out how to access just one of the two numbers. For us ordinary mortals, BusyBox has ttysize h and ttysize w.

W

whoami — print the Linux user's name

(A Unix command available in /system/bin.)

Prints the current Linux user's name, for example a0_u123.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Concepts

Back to index.

Concepts

Trying to run Unix commands on Android means you will come in contact with the Unix / Linux community. They are wonderful — hey, they give their work away for free, and often it's even unpaid work. But they often seem to assume that you know more than you actually do. Or maybe it's just me.

Since I remember how it feels to read through documentation and only understand half of it (like, yesterday and the day before), I'll try to document all concepts mentioned in the help pages of TTerm here.

All Android concepts are capitalized, e.g. "Android User", other concepts are not, e.g. "Linux user". Why? Because Google likes to change the names of Android concepts. And when some Google employee decides “Let's not call it preferences anymore, let's call it settings.”, then it's nice to be able to find the terms with grep to change them.

My personal favorite is the terminology of the SD cards. Some Google employee must have decided “Let's let the path /sdcard point to internal (non-removable) storage.” and some other employee must have thought “Well, then we'll need to call the real SD card something else, let's call it removable storage media.” and some other employee must have decided “Nah, I'll call it semi-permanent external storage or portable external storage instead.”. Most people gave up, everybody outside Google calls it internal SD card and external SD card, which Google stubbornly refuses to acknowledge.

Android OS System Properties

Android's Linux layer has system properties, I'll call them Android OS System Properties, that are different from the Java system properties. You can get them with getprop and set them with setprop.

CPU architecture

When I use CPU architecture, I mean the instruction set architecture.

Most Android devices have an ARM CPU architecture.

List of CPU architectures

Until now I've encountered these CPU architectures for Android devices:

arm

An ARM architecture has a name like ‘ARMv«n»’ (with ‘v’).

An ARM family has a name like ‘ARM«n»’ or ‘ARM Cortex-A‹n›’ (without ‘v’).

For example, the ARM family ARM11 uses the ARM architecture ARMv6.

arm64, aka aarch64

A 64-bit versions of ARM.

mips
x86

The 32-bit versions of PC CPUs.

An i686 ("P6 microarchitecture") is a x86.

x86-64, aka x64, x86_64, amd64

The 64-bit versions of PC CPUs.

For lists of CPU architectures, consult:

Wikipedia's "Comparison of instruction set architectures"
Wikipedia's "List of instruction sets"

Find out the CPU architecture

TODO How do you find out your device's CPU architecture? This looks promising:

getprop | sort | fgrep ro.product.cpu
ro.product.cpu.abi]: [armeabi-v7a]
ro.product.cpu.abi2]: [armeabi]
ro.product.cpu.abilist]: [armeabi-v7a,armeabi]
ro.product.cpu.abilist32]: [armeabi-v7a,armeabi]
ro.product.cpu.abilist64]: []

TODO Find out how terms like arm, armeabi and armeabi-v7a are related.

Custom ROM

When you buy an Android device, the device's preinstalled version of Android is called the stock ROM.

For some devices, people have built custom ROMs to replace the stock ROM, for example LineageOS. Custom ROMs are usually alternative versions of Android, but could even be a different operating system.

Installing a Custom ROM usually involves "unlocking the boot loader", which is outside the scope of this documentation, or rooting.

LineageOS

LineageOS is a popular Custom ROM that supports many Android devices.

It's very similar to ordinary Android, its main benefits is that it doesn't include all the additional junk that most manufacturers add to Android, and that you can often get newer versions of LineageOS when your manufacturer stops updating your device's Android. It's the successor of the popular CyagenMod.

I regularly test TTerm on LineageOS.

Distribution

See Shells and distributions.

Environment variables

Linux uses environment variables for configuration.

The set of all environment variables is called environment. To see it, use env or env | sort | more.

To set an environment variable in a shell, use:

export VAR='value' # (1)
export VAR="value" # (2)
export VAR=value   # (3)

In case (1) you must quote a single quote ' as '\''. In case (2) you must quote the four characters $ \ " ` as \$ \\ \" \` (and there may be additional characters depending on your shell). Strings quoted with single or double quotes can contain newlines. If you "get stuck" in a continuation string, press Control-C to get out.

Case (3) is only safe if the value does not contain whitespace or special characters. You must quote whitespace and many special characters with \.

To check that you got the quoting right, print an environment value with echo "$VAR" (the quotes are necessary if the value contains special characters).

When you start a command or subprocess, it inherits a copy of the environment. Changes in the copy are not visible in the original environment.

Do not confuse environment variables with shell variables. You set them similarly with VAR='value' or VAR="value", without using export. Shell variables are only used by the shell, they are not part of the environment and not passed to commands or subprocesses. For example PWD holds the local directory and PS1 the prompt.

To get a list of all shell variables and environment variables, use set or set | more.

Files

File access rights

Unix uses the term file mode for file access rights or file permissions, you change them with chmod.

Links

Unix supports soft links, also called "symbolic links", and hard links, which you can create with ln.

SD card

The SD cards are my personal favorite of confusing Android terminology. Some Google employee must have decided “Let's let the path /sdcard point to internal (non-removable) storage.” and some other employee must have thought “Well, then we'll need to call the real SD card something else, let's call it removable storage media.” and some other employee must have decided “Nah, I'll call it semi-permanent external storage or portable external storage instead.”. Most people gave up, everybody outside Google calls it internal SD card and external SD card, which Google stubbornly refuses to acknowledge.

External SD card

Some Android devices support a real SD card. Android has made such a mess of it that I won't even try to document it until a later release.

Internal SD card

Most current Android devices have a simulated SD card. It's usually called Internal SD Card, sometimes "emulated SD card" or "virtual SD card".

Since Android 4.2, the Internal SD Card of the current user must be reachable with /sdcard/.

TODO Document this: To access /sdcard, you must give TTerm the Permission Storage.

SELinux

Android includes SELinux, which stands for Security Enhanced Linux, which is about all I know about it. If I find out a use for SELinux TTerm, I'll document it here.

Shell

Android runs on top of a (small) Linux layer. To call Linux commands interactively, you need a shell and a terminal emulator.

The shell executes the Linux commands that you type. The corresponding thing in Windows are the two "command shells" cmd and powershell.

Linux offers many different shells. All of them will let you type commands and arguments, and set environment variables, as long as you quote special characters. They also contain a programming language to write shell scripts, but I sincerely hope that we won't need that for TTerm, since it lies somewhere between a surreal dream and a nightmare.

For more details, see Shells and distributions.

Further reading

A shell is a "command line interpreter", abbreviated CLI, read more about CLI shells and command-line interfaces.

Storage

External Storage

An Android device must support External Storage.

Currently, it's usually an Internal SD Card sometimes also an External SD Card, rarely only an External SD Card.

Internal Storage

Every app gets its own private Internal Storage. By default, it is in

/data/user/‹user id›/‹package name›/

The Internal Storage is deleted when you uninstall the app.

TTerm's Internal Storage

TTerm's Internal Storage for the default Android User with the User ID 0 is in

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/

For the User ID 0, that path is a soft link to

/data/data/de.t2h.tterm/

Sharing Internal Storage

Up to Android 6, it was possible to share the Internal Storage of an app with other apps by making it world readable or world writable. This is no longer possible in Android 7+.

This does not depend on the version of Android running on your device, only on the version the app is compiled for.

Up to Android 6, this was possible because the file access rights of an Internal Storage like /data/data/de.t2h.tterm/ were as follows (you need a rooted device to do this on your own device):

$ su -c "ls -god /data"
drwxrwx--x  38 4096 2018-02-01 17:56 /data

$ su -c "ls -god /data/data"
drwxrwx--x 153 8192 2018-02-11 00:09 /data/data

$ su -c "ls -god /data/data/de.t2h.tterm"
drwx-----x   6 4096 2018-02-08 00:13 /data/data/de.t2h.tterm

Note that all directories have the rights --x for "other", which means that other apps can't list the contents of the directory, but can access contents of the directory if they know their files name.

Apps compiled for Android 7 have these file access rights:

$ su -c "ls -god /data/data/de.t2h.tterm"
drwx------   6 4096 2018-02-08 00:13 /data/data/de.t2h.tterm

That's why you can't share Internal Storage anymore.

Terminal, terminal emulator

Android runs on top of a (small) Linux layer. To call Linux commands interactively, you need a shell and a terminal emulator.

TTerm is the terminal emulator. It displays your input (what you type) and the commands' output, but it doesn't actually execute any Linux commands. That's the job of the shell.

For more details, see Shells and distributions.

Further reading

Read more about terminal emulators.

Terminal settings

See stty, particularly stty sane.

If you have trouble with the terminal settings in Emacs, see Emacs terminal size and settings.

Terminal size

It's surprisingly difficult to ensure that the currently running command always knows the current terminal size.

If all goes well, you can query the terminal size with stty size.

If something gets messed up and Linux doesn't know the current terminal size, use stty rows and stty cols to set it.

If you have trouble with the terminal size in Emacs, see Emacs terminal size and settings.

Further reading

The excellent article The TTY demystified.

User

Android User

Since Android 4.2, some Android devices support more than one Android User.

The default Android User has the Android User ID 0.

An Android User is not a Linux user.

Linux user

A Linux user is not the same as an Android User. It's a user in the Linux layer that Android runs on, for example system or root.

Each app runs as a separate Linux user. For example, TTerm might run as the Linux user a0_u123, where a0 is the Android User ID of the default Android User, The number after u will be different on every device.

The command whoami prints the Linux user's name.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Configuration

Back to index.

Settings

Section "Text"

Setting Default to UTF-8

If you use non-ASCII characters like "á ä æ ı š б", you'll want to check this checkbox.

Android's default shell Mksh handles non-ASCII characters correctly.

LATER If you use the shell Bash, you'll also have to configure Bash correctly. I'll add more details when I figure out how to add Bash to TTerm.

Section "Shell"

Setting Command line

When TTerm starts, it executes this command line.

The default command line is:

/system/bin/sh -

TODO The single hyphen is a leftover from TEA. As far as I can discern it marks the end of options and start of arguments. Since there are neither options nor arguments it should be unnecessary, so I'll remove it in a future release.

If you want to execute code each time you open a window in TTerm, for exeample to set environment variables or shell variables, you have two options:

You can add the switch -l to make sh a login shell. Then sh will execute the file ~/.profile, where ~ is an abbreviation for $HOME.

Or you can set the environment variable ENV. The usual name of the configuration file is $HOME/.mkshrc. Since $HOME and ~ do not work here, you have to look up the full path first. On my device it's below /data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm. This works:

/system/bin/env ENV="/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/files/home/.mkshrc" sh

Yes, it's ridiculously complex.

The command line must begin with a full path to an executable command.

TODO If you specify a non-existing or unreadable file, TTerm will silently execute the default /system/bin/sh - instead. I'll change that in a future release.

The rest of the line is interpreted as arguments. The arguments can be quoted with double quotes. Inside double quotes you can escape a quote with a backslash. No other processing is performed. You can't use variables.

For example,

/system/bin/echo $PATH "a \" b"

will print $PATH a " b.

But you can let the shell expand variables for you:

/system/bin/sh -c "echo $PATH"

will print the value of $PATH and exit.

You can set environment variables and execute commands in $PATH using env, for example:

/system/bin/env VAR1="value 1" VAR2="value 2" sh

sets the environment variables VAR1 and VAR2, then searches sh in the paths of the environment variable PATH.

Setting Initial command

The initial command is sent to the shell as user input, i.e. as if you had typed it.

Setting Close window on exit

This setting is now off by default. When the command in the window exits, simply press Enter to close the window.

Setting Verify PATH entries

Removes unreadable paths from the environment variable PATH.

For example, the default value of PATH is:

/sbin:/vendor/bin:/system/sbin:/system/bin:/system/xbin

If this setting is checked, PATH will be reduced to:

system/bin:/system/xbin

If you have a rooted device, you might prefer to leave this unchecked, to keep those path entries for when you use su.

Settings Allow PATH extension and Allow PATH prepend

This will be replaced by a different concept in a future release of TTerm, since it does not work with apps compiled for Android 7+.

It still works with apps compiled for Android 4.4 to Android 6. This does not depend on the version of Android running on your device, only on the version the app is compiled for, see Sharing Internal Storage.

Setting HOME folder

Sets the environment variable $HOME which points to your home directory.

Change: Since version 0.2.1 (2018-01-30), the default for the setting HOME folder and the environment variable $HOME has changed from

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/app_HOME

to

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/files/home

You can confinue to use the old value if you prefer it, but if you uninstall and reinstall TTerm it default to the new value.

Environment variables

See the explanation of environment variables in Linux.

If you want to set environment variables or shell variables each time you open a window in TTerm, place them in the file ~/.profile, where ~ is an abbreviation for $HOME. Then add the switch -l to the setting Command line to make sh start as a login shell.

List of relevant environment variables

The following environment variables are relevant for TTerm:

$ENV — shell initialzation file

see Android's shell.

$HOME — your home directory

By default, TTerm sets it to

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/files/home

You can configure it in the setting HOME folder. Or you can set it in one of your shell's initialization files. For an example, see Android's shell.

Change: Since version 0.2.1 (2018-01-30), the default for the setting HOME folder and the environment variable $HOME has changed from

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/app_HOME

to

/data/user/0/de.t2h.tterm/files/home

You can confinue to use the old value if you prefer it, but if you uninstall and reinstall TTerm it default to the new value.

$LD_LIBRARY_PATH — list of paths to search for libraries, separated by colons

For example, Bash needs the library libncurses.so.

$PATH — list of paths to search for commands, separated by colons

On my devices, the default value for PATH is:

/sbin:/vendor/bin:/system/sbin:/system/bin:/system/xbin

If the setting Verify PATH entries is checked, PATH will be reduced to:

system/bin:/system/xbin

On my devices the default value of PATH is hardcoded in the binary /init. It can be set by the system initialization files in /init.* and the shell's initialization files.

You can set PATH in the shell's initialization files or with env as described under the setting Command line.

TODO I'll explain more about the system initialization files and the shell's initialization files in a future release.

$TERM — terminal type

Configure it in the setting Terminal type, or in one of your shell's initialization files.

The setting Terminal type offers the values:

linux
screen (default)
screen-256color
vt100
xterm

Changing this setting also changes the codes that TTerm sends for some Fn key combinations.

You have to restart the shell after changing TERM.

$TERMINFO — path to the Terminfo database

I'll write more on $TERM and $TERMINFO when time allows.

Physical keyboard

If you have problems with a physical keyboard, try the following steps:

The most important step to get non-ASCII characters like "á ä æ ı š б א" is in TTerm's Settings, where you have to check the checkbox Default to UTF-8.

You might have to configure your shell for UTF-8 input. Bash is particularly picky.

To test without the shell getting in the way, start a program like cat or vi.

You have to set the correct language-dependent keyboard layout for your physical keyboard.

In some versions of Android, the virtual keyboard interacts with the physical keyboard, so you also have to set the correct virtual keyboard.

The exact steps depend on your device and Android version. For example, this sets Google's virtual keyboard "Gboard" with a German layout on a standard Android 7 device. Device- and version-dependant steps are marked with (*).

Start the Android app "Settings".

You should see "Settings" at the top left. (*)

Search for "Languages & input" or something similar, and press it. (*)

You should see "Languages & input" or something similar at the top left. (*)

Press "Physical keyboard". (*)

You should see "Physical keybard" or something similar at the top left. (*)

If you see a list of virtual keyboards, select the virtual keyboard "Gboard". (*)

You should see "Keyboard layouts" or something similar at the top left. (*)

Select the correct layout, e.g. "German, Android keyboard".

Return to TTerm.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Features

Back to index.

Support for different keyboards

I test TTerm regularly with the on-screen keyboards:

Swype, my current favorite
Google's GBoard

and occasionally with the on-screen keyboards:

Hacker's Keyboard
Multiling O Keyboard
Samsung's keyboard on a Samsung Galaxy Tab S2 8.0 WiFi (2016), SM-T713, with Android 7

and occasionally with Bluetooth keyboards.

There are a surprising amount of differences between on-screen keyboards. If you find bugs on your favorite on-screen keyboard, send a bug report to thorbj.hansen@gmail.com.

You currently must set the setting input mode to character based, then typing works in all keyboards I've tested (where typing means that you press a key, release it, then press the next key).

Swiping (also called gesture typing) is a different matter. Every swipe keyboard seems to behave differently, so I'll return to that later.

Tested keyboards:

Keyboard | Current state
Gboard | As of version 0.1.6 in July 2017, typing works, swiping doesn't. `Ctrl´ and `Fn´ finally work.
Hacker's Keyboard | As of version 0.1.6 in July 2017, typing works.
Multiling O Keyboard | As of version 0.1.6 in July 2017, typing works, swiping doesn't.
Samsung's Keyboard | I've tested Samsung's keyboard on a Samsung Galaxy Tab S2 8.0 WiFi (2016), SM-T713, with Android 7. As of version 0.1.6 in July 2017, typing works, swiping also works (with the setting input mode is set to character-based).
Swype Keyboard | As of version 0.1.6 in July 2017, typing works, swiping doesn't.

Other keyboards:

Keyboard | Current state
a.i.type keyboard Free | I won't test this keyboard until they support an English QUERTZ layout. (Some German idiot decided to swap Y and Z so zou can't tzpe on anz other kezboard when zou have learned to tzpe on a German kezboard.)

If you find bugs on a different keyboard, send a bug report to thorbj.hansen@gmail.com.

Devices

I test TTerm regularly on:

a rooted Samsung Galaxy Tab S 10.5 WiFi (SM-T800, chagallwifi) with a 10" screen and LineageOS 14.1 (equivalent to Android 7.1 Nougat)
a rooted Samsung Galaxy Tab S2 8.0 WiFi (2016), SM-T713 that has a 8" screen and Android 7

I occasionally test on:

an unrooted Galaxy S3 Neo (GT-I9301I) with a 4.8" screen and Android 4.4

If you find bugs an a different device, send a bug report to thorbj.hansen@gmail.com.

Changes to TEA

TTerm has the same features as TEA, with the changes listed below.

For detailed changes, see the changelog.

Added features

Extra keys for `Ctrl´, `Tab´, `Esc´, `/, `-´, the cursor keys and `Fn´, so that you can continue using your favorite on-screen keyboard. The cursor keys have auto-repeat. For details, see Usage: Keyboard.

Key combinations with `Ctrl´, `Esc´ and `Fn´ currently only work when the setting input mode is set to character-based.

Suggestions for swiped words do not overwrite consecutive text. (As of 2017-07, this no longer works, I'll investigate it later.)

Some swipe keyboards display a suggestion which you have to commit, e.g. by pressing space or a punctuation key, or discard, e.g. by pressing backspace. For an example, try out the Google keyboard.

When typing in the middle of a line, TEA's suggestion overwrites the following text until you commit. TTerm tries to move the following text to the right. (That's not always the right thing to do, but in most cases it is more intuitive than TEA's approach.)

Example: Select the Google keyboard. Enter one two. Put the cursor on t. Enter hello without pressing space. Now TEA shows one hello, and TTerm shows one hellotwo. When you press space, TEA inserts hello and shows two again. So no text is lost, but I find TEA's behavior very confusing.

Local help files that you can read when you are offline.
The setting Close window on exit is now off by default. When the command in the window exits, simply press Enter to close the window.

Removed features

TTerm requires Android 4.4 or newer to run.

At the moment, TTerm's GUI is in English, and I have no plans to translate the GUI to other languages.

To clarify: Programs running inside TTerm can run in any language, but TTerm's menu and settings are in English.

If you want your GUI in another language, use TEA.

Changed features

I've changed some of the mappings for `Ctrl´ and `Fn´, see Usage: Keyboard.

TTerm – Planned features and known bugs

Back to index.

Planned features

Put sources on GitHub.

Keyboard

Add an `Alt´/`Meta´ key .
Make the additional keys user-configurable.
Provide a configurable on-screen character picker.

Get swipe to work for

Swype

Google's Gboard

Other swipe keyboards

Can we support word-based input?

As described in bug 001, word-based input (with a suggestion row) does not work with `Ctrl´ and `Esc´.

I'm not sure if this can be fixed when you type directly to the terminal. For example take the Emacs keyboard shortcut `Ctrl-x f´. Can we tell the IME that `f´ is part of the shortcut, not the start of a new word? There are analogous problems with keys like `a´ and `i´ in vi.

Maybe we could provide a button to toggle between character- and word-based input next to the `Ctrl´ button?

Or we could use an idea from VX ConnectBot and provide a separate input field where you swipe a whole line at a time, and send it to the terminal when you're done. But then you can't use file completion in the shell, nor use keyboard shortcuts in editors.

Flow control

If TTerm does not respond to key presses, you might have switched "flow control" on with `Ctrl+S´. When you switch flow control off with `Ctrl+Q´, the terminal will process all pending input. This is so confusing that I'll add a setting to switch it off in a future version of TTerm.

Settings

Add explanations to the settings.
In the font size settings, show the resulting number of columns and rows.

Terminal

Find out how to make `C-l´ clear the screen in Android's default shell Mksh and in the Bash that comes with BusyBox by Burrows, or provide an alternative.

Make "alternate screen" support optional

Console programs (i.e. programs that write to any part of the screen, like Emacs, less and vi, as opposed to CLI commands that only write to the end of the screen buffer) must use Termcap's ti or Terminfo's smcup capability when they start, and Termcap's te or Terminfo's rmcup capability when they end.

On terminals that support an "alternate screen", ti/smcup also switch to the alternate screen, and te/rmcup switch back. The result is that quitting a program like less or vi removes its output, which is extremely annoying when you use them to look up something that you want to use afterwards. So we'll provide a way to switch it off.

You should actually be able to configure that with $TERM (the setting Report terminal type and $TERMINFO, but that does not seem to work for several programs out in the wild.

Touch support

Support selections. The obvious gesture "touch & drag" is already used to scroll. Also add paste button?

Known bugs

Keyboard

Bug 001, low prio: Key combinations with `Ctrl´, `Esc´ and `Fn´ currently only work when the setting Input mode is set to character-based. There are analogous problems with keys like `a´ and `i´ in vi.

Bug 003, low prio: The keyboard disappears after a long inactivity, but the buttons stay.

Fix: Tap screen twice.

Bug 005, Alt-Gr does not work on hardware keyboards.

Bug 006: The additional keys are too big on phones in portrait mode. Choose an appropriate default font size.

Fix: Set "extra keys' size" in settings.

Terminal

Bug 002, high prio: Programs get confused when screen height changes

I've seen the problem often in Emacs, sometimes in Vi (which I only use rarely).

The problems are not always the same. Sometimes Emacs recovers easily by running this function:

(defun x ()
  (interactive)
  (redraw-frame (selected-frame)))

Other times you need to suspend Emacs and execute

stty rows 32 # Or whatever number is appropriate.

In Unix, the terminal must inform the foreground job when when the window height changes by sending the signal WINCH ("window change"). Which part of the code handles that?

Other tasks

See TODOs in source files.

TTerm – Rooting

Back to index.

Rooting

You do not need to root your device to use TTerm. Some of the things described in these help pages may require root, but they are optional.

So what's this rooting?

On a rooted device, any app can request "root permissions". In TTerm, you can run programs as "root" using su. Root is also called "superuser", and is the Linux equivalent of an "Administrator" in Windows.

Since root lets you circumvent most restrictions on an Android device, most manufacturers do not support it. So the Android community needs to find a way to root the devices anyway. Even on devices that support root like Google's Nexus devices it can be a complicated procedure.

So prepare yourself for some days of online research, confusion and several tries before you get it to work. Be aware that a mistake may "brick" your device, that is, render it into an expensive and useless brick. (A "soft bricked device" can be fixed, a "hard bricked device" can't be fixed.) Back up everything before you start, since a successful rooting may delete all data on your device - and unsuccessful rootings may delete even more.

The best starting points for rooting that I have found are:

http://www.xda-developers.com/root
http://www.androidcentral.com/root

Changing files in /system

LATER I'll explain how to change files in /system in a future release.

Copyright (C) 2014-2018 Thorbjørn Hansen

TTerm – Shells and distributions

Back to index.

Shells and distribuitions

Android's shell in TTerm
BusyBox in TTerm
Bash in TTerm
Termux in TTerm
Debian in TTerm

About shells and distribuitions

Android runs on top of a (small) Linux layer. To call Linux commands interactively, you need a "shell" and a "terminal emulator".

TTerm is the terminal emulator. It displays your input (what you type) and the commands' output, but it doesn't actually execute any Linux commands. That's the job of the shell. The shell actually understands your input and calls the Linux commands that you specify. The corresponding thing in Windows are the two "command shells" cmd and powershell.

Linux offers many different shells. This chapter lists some alternatives that I've tested in TTerm.

The shell contains some built-in commands, also called built-ins, like cd to change the shell's current directory. But most commands are not part of the shell, even basic commands like ls to list the contents of a directory, or cp to copy a file A Linux distribution is a prepackaged sets of Linux commands that you can install.

Linux also offers many different distribuitions. This chapter lists some alternatives that I've tested in TTerm.

Further reading

I'll try to explain everything that I found difficult when I started using Linux on Android. But you need familiarity with Linux or Unix to understand this. If you don't understand anything that's written here, have a look at a book about Linux for beginners before you continue. Yes, a book about Linux, not a book about Android.

If you just want to understand the terms on this page:

Read more about terminal emulators.
A shell is a "command line interpreter", abbreviated CLI, read more about CLI shells and command-line interfaces.
Read more about Linux distributions.

TTerm – Usage

Back to index.

GUI

The following features are not immediately obvious:

Toggle the on-screen keyboard with a tap on the screen or with the menu item "Toggle soft keyboard".

Press and hold the screen for the context menu "Edit text", which offers:

Select text
Copy all
Paste
Send control key (now also on a separate button)
Send fn key (now also on a separate button)

On-screen Keyboard

Toggle the on-screen keyboard with a tap on the screen or with the menu item "Toggle soft keyboard".
Key combinations with `Ctrl´, `Esc´ and `Fn´ currently only work when the setting input mode is set to character-based. [Bug 001]

The modifier buttons `Ctrl´ and `Fn´ are "sticky" after one press, "locked" after two presses. A sticky modifier turns green and will modify the next key you press. A locked modifier turns red and will modify all keys you press until you press the modifier again.

The cursor also show the modifier state: > for sticky `Ctrl´, ▶ for locked `Ctrl´; < for sticky `Fn´, ◀ for locked `Fn´. But the different cursors are hard to distinguish when the cursor isn't over a space, so I'll probably remove that in a future version.

As in TEA, `Ctrl´ and `Fn´ can also be bound to an additional key: the jog ball, the `@´ key, the `Left Alt´ key, the `Right Alt´ key, the `Vol Up´ key, the `Vol Down´ key, the `Camera´ key. I'll change that in a future version of TTerm.

If your on-screen or hardware keyboard has a `Ctrl´ or `Fn´ key, they are independent of TTerm's `Ctrl´ and `Fn´ buttons.

Control keys

The control keys are currently:

Ctrl+Space | Ctrl+@ | NUL
Ctrl+A..Z | Ctrl+A..Z |
Ctrl+1 | Ctrl+[ | ESC
Ctrl+2 | Ctrl+\ |
Ctrl+3 | Ctrl+] |
Ctrl+4 | Ctrl+^ |
Ctrl+5 | Ctrl+_ |

I found this more intuitive than TEA's mappings. In a future version of TTerm, the mappings will be configurable.

Note that some control keys have a special meaning in Unix:

Ctrl+Q | Flow Control Off
Ctrl+S | Flow Control On
Ctrl+H | Backspace
Ctrl+I | Tab
Ctrl+J | Line Feed
Ctrl+M | Carriage Return

If TTerm does not respond to key presses, you might have switched "flow control" on with `Ctrl+S´. When you switch flow control off with `Ctrl+Q´, the terminal will process all pending input. This is so confusing that I'll add a setting to switch it off in a future version of TTerm.

Function keys

The function keys are currently:

Fn+Q | Home | | Fn+A | Left
Fn+W | Up | | Fn+S | Down
Fn+E | End | | Fn+D | Right
Fn+R | PageUp | | Fn+F | PageDown
| | | |
Fn+T | Tab | | Fn+1..9 | F1..F9
Fn+I | Insert | | Fn+0 | F10
Fn+X | Delete | | Fn+O | F11
| | | Fn+P | F12

I found this more intuitive than TEA's mappings. In a future version of TTerm, the mappings will be configurable.

Physical keyboard

TTerm should work with a physical keyboard, you might have to check the configuration.

Terminal settings

Setting the environment variable $TERM

Questions?

TTerm does not have its own community yet, but since it's based on TEA, you can consult their wiki and their Google+ community.

You can contact me at thorbj.hansen@gmail.com.